```json
{
  "exam_name": "Midterm Exam CSC 252 3 March 2023 Computer Science Department University of Rochester",
  "problems": [
    {
      "problem": "Problem 0",
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Have you been to TA office hours before?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "YES/NO"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "problem": "Problem 1",
      "problem_context": "Fixed-Point Arithmetics",
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Represent decimal number 24 in hexadecimal form."
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "18"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "b",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Represent octal (base 8) number 53 in decimal form and binary form."
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "43;101011"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "c",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider two unsigned binary numbers A=1011 and B=0101. Do the math below. Use as many bits as needed to precisely represent the results.",
              "subproblem_question": "What's the result of A+B?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What's the result of A-B?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What's the result of A*B?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "10000"
            },
            {
              "solution": "0110"
            },
            {
              "solution": "110111"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "problem": "Problem 2",
      "problem_context": "Floating-Point Arithmetics",
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider a decimal number F=-100.50:",
              "subproblem_question": "Give the binary representation of F:"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Put F into the normalized scientific notation:"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Write the significand in binary:"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "-1100100.1"
            },
            {
              "solution": "-1.1001001 x 2^6"
            },
            {
              "solution": "1001001"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "b",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider a hex value F=0x7f800000 that represents a floating point number encoded using the IEEE 754 single-precision format.",
              "subproblem_question": "What is the exponent value (in decimal)?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What does F represent?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "128"
            },
            {
              "solution": "Positive infinity"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "c",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Professor Bob teaches a computer science course, and he is designing the scoring system of a midterm exam. The exam consists of 64 multiple choice questions and students will receive 1 point for each correct answer, 0 point for leaving it blank, and -0.25 points for a wrong answer. To store all the possible scores, Bob wants to incorporate knowledge from CSC 252 to improve the space efficiency by designing a new floating point representation, which should meet three criteria: 1. The characteristics are compliant with the floating-point representations we discussed in class; 2. Can accurately represent any valid score; 3. Use as few bits as possible.",
              "subproblem_question": "How many bits are used for the significand in this new floating point representation?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "How many bits are used for the exponent fields in this new floating point representation?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What's the bias?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Can you use a fixed point representation for the same purpose? If yes, at least how many bits do you need? If not, explain the reason."
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "7"
            },
            {
              "solution": "4"
            },
            {
              "solution": "7=(2^(4-1))-1"
            },
            {
              "solution": "yes; 10"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "problem": "Problem 3",
      "problem_context": "Logic Design",
      "problem_figures": ["IMAGE", "TABLE", "IMAGE"],
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Assuming A2A2A1A0=(1001)2 and B2B2B1B0=(0001)2:",
              "subproblem_question": "If X=0, what is the value of P3P2P1P0?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "If X=1, what is the value of P3P2P1P0?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "0001"
            },
            {
              "solution": "1110"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "b",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Still assuming A2A2A1A0=(1001)2 and B2B2B1B0=(0001)2:",
              "subproblem_question": "If X=0, what is the value of Σ2Σ2Σ1Σ0?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "If X=1, what is the value of Σ2Σ2Σ1Σ0?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "1010"
            },
            {
              "solution": "1000"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "c",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Assume that the 1-bit full adder is implemented as shown in the figure below. The delay at each gate is 1 ps.",
              "subproblem_question": "What is the propagation delay of the 1-bit full adder?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What is the total propagation delay of the entire circuit shown at the beginning of this problem? Assuming that the XOR gates outside the full adder have a delay of 1ps, too."
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "3 ps"
            },
            {
              "solution": "9 ps"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "problem": "Problem 4",
      "problem_context": "Assembly Programming",
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider the following C code: struct Car{ char *model; int year; long mpg; }; struct Car myCars[2]; The following assembly is part of a function print_info(), which, as you can see, calls another function get_cars(), which initializes myCars and returns the pointer that points to myCars.",
              "subproblem_question": "What is the size (number of bytes) of struct Car, assuming proper alignment?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "At the end of line 5, what C variable does %rax contain? Express in C syntax."
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "At the end of line 9, what C variable does %rl contain? Express in C syntax."
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "24"
            },
            {
              "solution": "myCars[1].mpg"
            },
            {
              "solution": "myCars[0].model[3]"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "b",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider the following function p2. Its C code and assembly code are both partially given. Assuming that the input arguments to p2 are x=4, y=4. Then, use the rest of the assembly to find the return value of p2() given: unsigned long p2(unsigned long x, unsigned long y){ unsigned long t1= x + 2*y; unsigned long t2= . . . ; // intentionally hidden return t2; } // some irrelevant instructions at the beginning omitted",
              "subproblem_question": "Complete the three missing pieces in the assembly code."
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What is the byte contained in -8 (%rbp) after line 7?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What is the return value of p2?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "leaq; %rdx; %rax"
            },
            {
              "solution": "0xC"
            },
            {
              "solution": "3"
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "problem": "Problem 5",
      "problem_context": "Processor architecture",
      "parts": [
        {
          "part": "a",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "Consider a microarchitecture that is designed for an ISA with 256 instructions and 16 general-purpose registers. The ISA has a 16-bit address space. Assuming the opcode fields in all the instructions are encoded using the same amount of bits.",
              "subproblem_question": "If an instruction in this ISA takes the form of ins r1, r2, r3, where ins is the opcode, and r1, r2, and r3 are three general-purpose registers. How many bits are required to encode this instruction?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Assuming the jump instructions in this ISA are encoded using absolute addresses. What is the number of bits needed to encode a jump instruction?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "20"
            },
            {
              "solution": "24"
            }
          ]
        },
        {
          "part": "b",
          "subproblem": [
            {
              "subproblem_context": "A single-cycle processor has a cycle time of 30 ns. Consider two different pipelined implementations of the same processor, each with 5 and 10 stages, respectively. Assume that the stages divide the computation uniformly. In both pipelined processors, it takes 1 ns for the output of a stage to latch on to the pipeline registers.",
              "subproblem_question": "What is the shortest plausible clock period for the 5-stage pipelined processor?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What is the shortest clock period for the 10-stage pipelined processor?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What is the execution time per instruction in the 10-stage pipelined processor?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Assuming no pipeline stall of any kind, how long does it take to execute 50 instructions in the 5-stage pipeline?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Assuming no pipeline stall of any kind, how long does it take to execute 50 instructions in the 10-stage pipeline?"
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "Assuming no pipeline stall of any kind, express the total execution time of 50 instructions as a function of the pipeline stages T."
            },
            {
              "subproblem_question": "What number of pipeline stages will give you the minimum total execution time for 50 instructions?"
            }
          ],
          "answer": [
            {
              "solution": "7 ns"
            },
            {
              "solution": "4 ns"
            },
            {
              "solution": "39 ns (40 accepted)"
            },
            {
              "solution": "54*7=378 ns"
            },
            {
              "solution": "59*4=236 ns"
            },
            {
              "solution": "(x-1+50)*(30/x+1)"
            },
            {
              "solution": ""
            }
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
```